Preliminary Inventory to the Sig Mickelson Papers 1950-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
Sig Mickelson papers
1950-2000
82074
Mickelson, Sig
33 manuscript boxes (13.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Minutes of meetings, reports, memoranda, financial records, speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, interviews, conference papers, press releases, printed matter, and phonotapes, relating to broadcasting activities of Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, and to financing of American presidential election campaigns and media coverage of presidential nominating conventions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Radio Free Europe.; Radio Liberty (Munich, Germany); Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Radio broadcasting--Soviet Union.; Europe, Eastern.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Presidents--United States--Election.; Mass media--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations.; Phonotapes.
Container List
- Board of Directors (BOD) meeting minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
- Relocation studies (Box 1)
- BOD minutes, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
- Financial budgets (Box 2)
- Mickelson speeches (Box 2)
- BOD minutes, 1970s (Box 3)
- Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE/RL) fund (Box 3)
- BOD minutes, 1970s (Box 4)
- RL program schedule (Box 4)
- BOD minutes, 1970s (Box 5)
- Program review conference, 1976 (Box 5)
- Engineering/technical (Box 6)
- Portugal, Rádio Retransmissão Sociedade Anónima de Radio-Retransmissão (RARET) (Box 6)
- Markov murder (Box 6)
- Bombing, 1981 (Box 6)
- Communist Intelligence Services (Box 6)
- Radio Liberty (RL) program and budget, 1975 (Box 6)
- RL administration (Box 7)
- General accounting Office (GAO) report, 1976 (Box 7)
- Mickelson speeches (Box 7)
- Congressional hearings (Box 7)
- Corporate documents for a merged RFE/RL, Inc. (Box 7)
- Audience research reports (Box 7)
- Trip Briefing Books, 1976 (Box 8)
- RL Audience Research reports (Box 8)
- RL engineering (Box 9)
- Spain (Box 9)
- Olympics coverage study, 1976 (Box 9)
- RFE/RL and the Olympic Games. (Box 9)
  Includes documentation that describes RFE covering all Olympics in an organized form since Helsinki in 1952, except for Tokyo in 1964 on cost grounds. RL was less focused on Olympics, and only covered them since 1960
- Labor relations in Munich, 1975 (Box 9)
- RL press releases, 1951-1953 (Box 9)
- RL study, "Fifty Years of the Soviet Political Emigration, 1917-1967," by Oliver J. Frederickson (Box 10)
- Congressional briefings, 1976 (Box 10)
- GAO report, 1971 (Box 10)
- May 25, 1972 (Box 10)
- U.S. Government Monies Provided to Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty by the Comptroller General of the United States. Includes information on weekly program mix and budget data (Box 10)
- Budget review, 1976 (Box 11)
- Mickelson speeches (Box 11)
- Board for International Broadcasting (BIB) meeting, 1976 (Box 11)
- RFE/RL Board, 12 April 1976. (Box 11)
  Confidential Memorandum to the Files [SM] "relationships between BIB staff and this management of RFE and RL have been something less than warm and friendly..."
- Congressional hearings, 1977 (Box 11)
- Consolidation (Box 12)
- Voice of America (VOA) (Box 12)
- BBC (Box 12)
- RL audience research (Box 12)
- Pell amendment (Box 13)
- Consolidation (Box 13)
- GAO report, 1976 (Box 13)
- Relocation (Box 13)
- RFE president reports, 1950-1952 (Box 13)
- Church committee, 1976 (Box 13)
- RFE and RL history notes (Box 13)
- BIB-RFE/RL conflicts (Box 13)
- CIA relationships (Box 13)
- Budgets (Box 14)
- Olympics (Box 14)
- RFE Memos on technical facilities, 1950 (Box 14)
- Early history files for Mickelson book (Box 14)
- Hearings (Box 14)
- Wall Street Journal editorial on BIB and Radio's mess, 3 June 1980 (Box 14)
- Durkee, Hovey, Lester termination payments, 1976 (Box 14)
- BIB Board meeting notes, 1975 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous subjects, late 1970s early 1980s (Box 15)
- John Scott Reports. Includes a 5 June 1976 interview with Lang, a memo to Sig from John regarding April-May activities, and a draft speech (Box 15)
- Poland, 1981 (Box 15)
- Early history (Box 15)
- Reagan administration (Box 15)
- Poland, 1981 (Box 16)
- Counterattacks (Box 16)
- Labor Law (Box 16)
- Audience research (Box 16)
- Fund (Box 17)
- Budgets (Box 17)
- Miscellany (Box 17)
- Briefing book, 1975 (Box 17)
- 1975-1977 (Box 18)
- Congressional briefing books (Box 18)
- Budgets (Box 18)
- Budgets, 1975 (Box 19)
- Comptroller general study, 1981 (Box 19)
- Board, 1975 (Box 19)
- CRS study (Box 19)
- Book chapter (Box 19)
- BIB and trips, 1976 (Box 20)
- Embassy evaluations and state cables, 1976 (Box 21)
- Panel review of Polish broadcasts, Z. Brzezinski, William E. Griffith, Korbonski, Montias, Pipes, 13 April 1975 (Box 21)
- Draft chapter on news not in book (Box 21)
- Budget (Box 21)
- BIB (Box 21)
- RFE/RL pictures (Box 21)
- Sound recordings of people interviewed by Sig Mickelson
  A card file giving biographical information on each person connected in one way or the other with Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty is duplicated for each interview listing below. Card files are available in box 22
  - Abshire, David M., sound recording, 1 May 1982 (Box 22)
    Mickelson interviews Abshire concerning his activities with the federal government and foreign policy in the early 1970s. Topics of the conversation include, but are not limited to: Senator Clifford Case, Senator Fulbright, the State Department, Bill Rogers, the American Council, quasi-independent corporations within the government and congressional oversight, Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty, and the CIA's involvement with the radios. The sound quality indicates this interview took place over the telephone. Abshire was assistant secretary of state for congressional relations, 1971-72; chairman of the U.S. board of international broadcasting, 1974-77. Cassette 1. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003434
  - Arkus, Al, sound recording, 13 May 1981 (Box 22)
    Arkus talks about his time at Radio Free Europe, concentrating on the production side of broadcasting. The conversation begin with how Arkus got his start at RFE. He moved over from Gotham recording, where he had been effectively producing for RFE while working as a technician for Gotham, because RFE people were from newspapers. He notes that he was involved in radio since high school. When describing the production of the broadcasts, he covers several topics. He describes the RFE offices and studios in New York City. He details how the production needs drove what facilities they used and how they used them; in the process, he describes his effort to get RFE to use cart tapes. The conversation touches on Arkus' direction of plays for radio and other programming meant to catch the ear of the listeners. Arkus details covering three large events: the Olympics; elections, including concurrently interacting with four different services; and a Papal visit to America and live broadcast to Poland. He describes the technical routing of signals. He also speaks about professionalism at RFE and the personal fulfillment he's achieved working at the radios. Arkus joined RFE as a studio recording, technician in 1950, and was production manager of the New York production center, 1975-. Cassette 2. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003435
  - Baker, John, sound recording, 6-11 May 1981 (Box 22)
    Baker was a member of the European Bureau, D.O.S. assigned to RFE and RL liaison, 1971-1974. Cassette 46. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004648
  - Barrett, Edward W., sound recording, 11-12 October 1982; February 1983 (Box 22)
    In a wide ranging conversation, Mickelson interviews Barrett about various topics concerning Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty. Among these are various people within the federal government, especially the executive branch, State Department, and Wisner; the independence of the radios from politicians; and Voice of America, the Crusade for Freedom, and other related organizations. The interview includes profanity. The sound quality indicates this interview took place over the telephone. Barrett was a member, Free Europe corporation, 1949; director, RFE/RL, 1975-82. Cassette 56 consists of a sound recording of Sig Mickelson summarizing interviews with Barrett and two others, February 1983. Cassette 3, 56. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003436 and 82074_a_0004741
  - Bellus, Samuel, sound recording, 24 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Mickelson interviews Bellus about his life and work with the Czech-Slovak service of Radio Free Europe. Recounting his biography, Bellus explains how he was a member of parliament who eventually escaped Czechoslovakia when the communists came to power. After escaping to the American embassy in Vienna, Austria, he became involved in Radio Free Europe. He does not go into depth about his escape because the people who helped him escape are still in Czechoslovakia. Instead of immediately going to Munich, he wished to go to America, learn about the country, and become a citizen before working in Germany. The conversation then turns to his work in the Czech-Slovak service. Bellus explains how he came to head the service, and talks about various aspects of his work, for example, the relationship between offices in New York, London, and Munich. Bellus was a defector from the CSSR, 1948; director, RFE Czecho-Slovak service, 1976-. Cassette 4. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003437
  - Bena, Kamiel, sound recording, June 1981 (Box 22)
    Mickelson interviews Kamil Bena about the Czecho-Slovak service. The interview begins with Bena recounting how he got his start at RFE. He then talks about the Munich site before and after he joined. Speaking about the service generally, he describes his colleagues, comments on its method of operating as compared to the other services, and talks about the types of programming (music, news, etc.). The interview concludes with Bena reflecting on his dedication to RFE and the idealism within the building. Bena was senior editor, administrator, RFE Czecho-Slovak service, 1952-. Cassette 5. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003438
  - Bernard, Noel, sound recording, 25 June 1981 (Box 22)
    In a fast paced interview, Mickelson interviews Bernard about several topics. Bernard discusses his background, including stints in Rome, at the BBC, and at RFE/RL; RFE listening posts; why he is not proud of some of his work at RFE in the 1950s; establishing credibility and what attracts the Romanian people; acquiring documents via a dissident and the reaction of the government; a staff member in Paris that was beaten up; and an earthquake in Bucharest. He spends some time discussing feedback RFE gets from those in Romania. He says most of the letters ask how one gets out of the country, followed by letters concerning the pop music they broadcast, explaining this is how they want to hook young listeners. He says they also get letters of denunciation. Cassette 5. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003438
    Bernard talks about an earthquake and the following events; he also talks about a controversial event in 1979 related to churches and fascists. Following this, Bernard discusses Holtzman (sp?) and her actions. Bernard was director, RFE Romanian service to 1982. Cassette 6. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003546
  - Bivar, Manuel, sound recording, 30 May 1981 (Box 22)
    Divar discusses broadcasting in Portugal, touching on various aspects. Much of the interview was recorded at a very low level on the original cassette; this portion is unintelligible due to the low signal-to-noise ratio. On the second side of the cassette, Mickelson repeats a story about the first transmission to Czechoslovakia. Bivar was chief engineer of RFP, 1950-51; liaison with Free Europe Inc., 1951-. Cassette 7. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003547
  - Bobinsky, Bogdan, sound recording, October 1981 (Box 22)
    Bobinsky speaks about leaving the Ukraine before recalling various aspects about working at RFE/RL. He also discusses his family. Bobinsky was a Ukrainian technician in the Washington office, 1975-. Cassette 8. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003548
  - Bodin, Thomas, sound recording, 15 October 1981; 25 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Bodin describes many aspects of the news divisions of the radios with a special emphasis on the early 1960s transition of RFE from a political organization with a military background to a journalism organization. The conversation begins with the scope of RFE/RL news division, especially as it relates to the international news organizations. He says that RFE broadcasts as local radio and focuses on local interest. Following, the men discuss the quality and professionalism of the news division. Bodin says non-journalists originally set up the radios to further a political agenda and thus were not professional news organizations. He credits increased travel between east and west by the 1960s in causing the radios to change their scope and organization. The conversation then turns to a lengthy discussion of the content of the news broadcasts. Following, they discuss the bureaus: the function, purpose, and number. Some time is spent on the relationship between the New York and Munich offices. Other topics discussed include: plagiarism in the New York office; production values of broadcasts; news services RFE subscribed to; Radio Liberty news operation before the merger (Bodin did not know much about it, but didn't like it); Russ Hill and other individual correspondents; and top news stories memos to the various language services. Bodin was successively a member of the news staff, RFE Munich, bureau chief in London, bureau chief in New York, and bureau chief in Washington, D.C. Cassette 9, 10. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003552 and 82074_a_0003553
  - Braden, Thomas W., sound recording, 5 May 1982 (Box 22)
    The interview concerns the involvement of the CIA, Office of Policy Coordination, and Frank Wisner on the Radios. Braden was the director of Intelligence Operations Division of the CIA, 1951-54, with responsibility for RFE liaison. Cassette 11, 56. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003878 and 82074_a_0004741
  - Brown, James F., sound recording, 1-2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Brown describes RFE/RL following the Polish declaration of martial law in 1981, monitoring Warsaw television, what gets put into stories, how RFE/RL's hard news differed from its soft news and other features, and states RFE/RL never got trapped in stories. Brown was director of Radio Free Europe, 1977-. Other topics include: the biography of Brown; colleagues at the radios, especially Novak; reforms at the radios, especially the beginning of RFE/RL-created research; Jozef Swiatlo's defection and RFE interviews; flourishing of RFE; religious factors and generational differences at Radio Liberty; RFE as compared to the Voice of America and the BBC; and the involvement of the CIA. When asked, Brown believes the aim of the Radios is to make the public opinion of the countries informed and alert, with an emphasis on alertness. He says the key is to keep the view of Eastern Europeans that RFE is on their side. He calls 1957-62 the most important years of RFE. Cassette 12, 13. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003891 and 82074_a_0003892
  - Bush, Keith, sound recording, 23 June 1981 (Box 22)
    This interview covers a wide range of topics. It begins with Bush's biography--his educational background and how he came to work at Radio Free Europe. It moves to changes he's seen in the organization over the years. He says the biggest is the emphasis on nationalities, with another noticeable change being the types of programming moving away from the timeless to the topical. The interview moves to the topic of RL employees' familiarity with the covered nations, which includes the scope of RL's programming--with an emphasis on health news. Mickelson concludes by inquiring about the non-Russian Soviet republics, where RL gets its researchers, and how Bush hopes to expand the research division. Bush was director of the research department of Radio Liberty. Cassette 14. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003893
  - Campbell, Earnal, sound recording, 17 June 1981; 22 June 1981 (Box 22)
    This interview concerns technical aspects of RFE/RL's broadcasts. Topics covered include: how Campbell joined RFE/RL, engineering consultants RFE/RL used, installations, studio layout and design, antennas, transmitting frequencies, jamming by the Soviet Union, transmitting angles and signal loss, monitoring, and personnel. The second interview concerns the 1981 bombing. Campbell was at home, about a half kilometer from the building, yet felt the blast. He further mentions that his building suffered a broken window. He goes through how he went to the RFE/RL building, got through security, and surveyed the damage. He explains how they kept broadcasts going, that the bombing did not fulfill its goal of knocking RFE/RL off the air. He says the Czech newsroom was the only production facility destroyed. Campbell was chief engineer, RFE/RL, 1975-82. Cassette 15, 16. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003897 and 82074_a_0003898
  - Cline, Ray, sound recording, 6 May 1982 (Box 22)
    The interview concerns the involvement of the CIA, Office of Policy Coordination, and Frank Wisner on the Radios. Cline was a long-time CIA officer familiar with RFE and RL stories. Cassette 11. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003878
  - Cook, Richard, sound recording, 1 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Starting with the topic of Polish martial law, Cook explains the relationships between the various language services of RFE/RL. He is 'astounded' by the isolation between language services and argues there would be no interaction were it not for a common English-speaking management. Included in his remarks are how many services were reluctant to cover Polish news due to distance without his pressure and about Soviet involvement in Afghanistan and central Asia. Cook was director, nationalities staff, RL Munich. Cassette 17. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003899
  - Cummings, Richard, sound recording, 22 June 1981 (Box 22)
    This interview concerns security measures before, during, and after the 1981 bombing. Cummings was director of security for RFE/RL, 1980-. Cassette 18. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004051
  - De Brauw, Pieter J. W., sound recording, 14-19 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Cassette 19. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0000202
  - Dennis, George, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Dennis was the personal representative of the president of RLC in Spain, Cassette 20. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004060
  - De Weydenthal, Jan, sound recording, 18 December 1980 (Box 22)
    Cassette 21. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004063
  - Dunning, John, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    This interview concerns Senator Case's speech, employee morale, and the influence of politicians on the Radios. Dunning was director of operations and planning, Free Europe Inc., 1955-75. Cassette 11. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003878
  - Eberl, Ingeborg, sound recording, June 1981 (Box 22)
    Eberl describes being in wing B of the RFE building during the bombing. Her memory is vivid, recalling many details about that night. The content of the interview gives the impression Mickelson conducted the interview at the RFE/RL site in Munich. Eberl was a telephone operator, RFE/RL Munich, injured in bombing. Cassette 5. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003438
  - Edwards, James, sound recording, 22 June 1981; 1 June 1982 (Box 22)
    This interview concerns Edwards' actions during the very first days of martial law in Poland. This includes several parts about the qualifications for running stories. Edwards was director of the central news division of RFE/RL. Cassette 12, 18. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003891 and 82074_a_0004051
  - Evdokimov, Evdokim, sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Evdokimov was a member, RFE Bulgarian service Munich; chairman, Munich unit of ANG. Cassette 22. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004074
  - Fallis, Hugh, sound recording, 15 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Fallis discusses the transmitters the radios use. The conversation also touches on jamming and transmission paths. Fallis was successively manager of the transmitter base at Radio Liberty Lampertheim, engineer at Radio Liberty in New York, engineer for RFE/RL Inc., L&L, and engineer for RFE/RL Inc. in Munich. Cassette 9, 10. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003552
  - Federspiel, Per, sound recording, 5 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Federspiel, a Danish lawyer, was a founding member [WEAC?] [Singe?], 1959; active in European and North Atlantic Internationa organizations. Cassette 23. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004077
  - Fedoseyev, Victor, sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Fedoseyev (Feddseyev) was a member, Russian features staff, RL Munich, 1972-. Cassette 37. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004581
  - Griffith, William E., sound recording, 24 November 1981 (Box 22)
    Griffith was policy adviser to the director of RFE Munich, 1952-59. Cassette 24. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004080
  - Grover, Allen, sound recording, August 1982 (Box 22)
    Grover was director of American Committee for freedom of people of USSR and successor organizations, 1975-76; called first meeting of incorporators. Cassette 25. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004082
  - Hart, Henry, sound recording, 18 December 1980 (Box 22)
    This interview concerns the audience, its reactions to RFE/RL, the amount of the population that listens to RFE/RL, and how RFE/RL conducts audience research. Hart was director, Audience and OP research, RFE. Cassette 26. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004089
  - Henze, Paul, recounted in a Sig Mickelson sound recording, 11 November 1981 (Box 22)
    This is a sound recording of Sig Mickelson recounting his interview with Henze. Due to the phone recorder malfunctioning and not recording, the actual interview of Henze was not recorded. Cassette 27. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004186
  - Houston, Lawrence, sound recording, 11-12 October 1982 (Box 22)
    The sound quality indicates this interview took place over the telephone. Houston was co-author, National Security Act of 1947; counsel to the Central Intelligence Agency. Cassette 3. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003436
  - Kingsley, Nathan, sound recording, 15 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Kingsley discusses various aspects of RFE's programming. Kingsley was director of news, Munich, late 1960s; vice president of public affairs and corporate secretary for RFE/RL, Inc. in Washington, D.C., 1976-82. Cassette 9. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003552
  - Kruzhin, Peter, sound recording, 25 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Kruzhin speaks through an interpreter about Radio Liberty. Cassette 28. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004191
  - Lang, Robert E., sound recording, 31 May 1981 (Box 22)
    Lang was the first director of Radio Free Europe, 1949-53. Cassette 29. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004195
  - Lester, Jane, sound recording, 5 May 1982 (Box 22)